A Finding Aid to the E. P. (Edgar Preston) and Constance Richardson papers, 1814-1996, bulk 1921-1996, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
- Correspondence, 1926-1988; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 4.6 Linear feet Boxes 2-6
  - General, 1926-1988; 3.1; Archival Resource Key; 3.3 Linear feet Boxes 2-5
    General correspondence is with colleagues, professional acquaintances, art critics and historians, galleries and dealers, museums, and other organizations regarding purchasing art for collections, authentications and attributions, publishing, news about friends and acquaintances, and general consultations. There is correspondence with Wayne Andrews, Archives of American Art, Castano Galleries, Lawrence Fleischman, James Thomas Flexner, Alfred V. Frankenstein, George Croce, Walter Heil, Earl Krentzin, Wilmarth Lewis, Russel Lynes, John Francis McDermott, Philadelphia Museum of Art, J. Hall Pleasants, Anna Rutledge, Charles Sellers, Smithsonian Institution, Regina Soria, Victor Spark, William Stevens, Robert Vose, William Woolfenden, and many others.
    Arranged in alphabetical order.
    - A, 1966-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Agnew, Geoffrey, 1967-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - American Art Journal, 1975-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Andrews, Wayne, 1966-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Archives of American Art, 1959-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Athenaeum of Philadelphia, 1969-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - B, 1934-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 46-47)
    - Barbeau, Dr. Marius, National Museum of Canada, 1947-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Bell, Whitfield J., 1966-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Boyd, Julian P., 1966-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 50-51)
    - Bowen, Catherine Drinker, 1967-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Buck, C. Douglass Jr., 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Burton, Irving, 1967-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - C, 1947-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Canaday, John, 1962-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Castano Galleries, 1960-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Childs Gallery, 1975-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Coe Kerr Gallery, 1970-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Coleman, Mrs. Bertram D., 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Colnaghi, P.D. & Co. Ltd, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Cramer, Hans H., 1967-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Crawford, Ralston, 1930; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - D, 1926-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - De Young Museum, 1978-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Dwight, Edward H., 1965-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - duPont, Edmund, 1968-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - E, 1968-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - F, 1943-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Fleischman, Lawrence, 1953-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Flexner, James Thomas, 1947-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Folie, Jacqueline, 1972-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Frankenstein, Alfred V., San Francisco Chronicle, 1947-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - G, 1966-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Groce, George C., 1946-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - H, 1930-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Harris, Paul S., 1967-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Heil, Dr. Walter, 1953-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Hendricks, Gordon, 1967-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Hirschl and Adler Galleries, 1967-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Hitchings, Sinclair, 1970-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Hubbard, Dr. Robert H., 1953-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - I, 1968-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - J, 1965-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - K, 1942-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Kennedy Galleries, 1966-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Kerslake, John, 1967-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Knoedler Gallery, 1968-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - L, 1960-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Large, James M., 1968-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Levitt, Dr. Irving, 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Lewis, Percy Wyndham, 1944-1948; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Lewis, Wilmarth S., 1966-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Lewis, Wilmarth S., 1966-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Longhi, Prof. Roberto, 1956-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Lynes, Russell, 1966-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - M, 1934-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
    - McDermott, John Francis, 1953-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - McNeil, Henry S., 1968-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Maiullo, Anthony, 1949-1954; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1969-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Middeldorf, Ulrich, 1947-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Morse, John D., 1948-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Mount, Charles M., 1967-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - N, 1959-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - O, 1966-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Oliver, Andrew, 1967-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - P-Q, 1944-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Peat, Wilbur D., 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Philadelphia Museum of Art, Commissioners of Fairmount Park, 1950-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 18-19)
    - Pierrot, George, 1969-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Pleasants, Dr. J. Hall, 1947-1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Portraits, Inc., 1966-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - R, 1959-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Representatives - U.S., 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Rutledge, Anna, 1941-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - S, 1941-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Schweitzer, M. R., 1970-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Scott Foundation, 1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Sellers, Charles C., 1954-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Sellers, Charles C., 1954-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Sizer, Theodore, 1956-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Smithsonian, Ripley, S. Dillon, 1968-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Smithsonian Art Commission, 1969-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Smithsonian Journal of History, 1965-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Soria, Mrs. Dino, 1962-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Spark, Victor D., 1961-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Speck, Adm. Robert, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Speight, Francis, 1968-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Stevens, William B., Jr., 1967-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Stone, James, 1968-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Stovell, Thomas P., 1968-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - T, 1940-1976; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Taylor, George W., 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Taylor, Newbold, 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - U-V, 1967-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Viteles, Morris S., 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Vose, Robert C., 1961-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - W-Z, 1945-1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 19-20)
    - Wells, William H.S., 1968-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Wittmann, Otto, 1966-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Woolfenden, William E., 1966-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Wright, Louis B., 1967-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - With Artists, 1942-1985; 3.2; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Boxes 5-6
    Generally scattered correspondence is with various artists concerning their artwork and exhibitions, interested collectors, advice, return of paintings, fellowships, and other topics. Most files contain only one or two letters. Among the numerous correspondents are Isabel Bishop, Louis Bouche, William Bostick, Eve Garrison, Edward Hopper, Irene Jungwirth, Yasuo Kuniyoshi, Hughie Lee-Smith, Reginald Marsh, Gerald Mast, Georgia O'Keeffe, Charles Sheeler, Walt Speck, and John Wedda. The greatest extent of correspondence is with Andrew Wyeth, Harold Cohn, and Frederick Simper. There is also one letter from Winston Churchill about a traveling Smithsonian exhibition of his paintings in Detroit.
    Arranged alphabetically by last name.
    - A-C, 1945-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 32)
      Correspondents include: Ivan Albright, Clarence Carter, Harry Bertoia, Isabel Bishop, Aaron Bohrod, William Bostick, Louis Bouche, Evalyn Brackett, Robert Broner, Charles Burchfield, James Calder, Frank Cassara, Ada G. Chaffee, Winston Churchill, and John Cornish.
    - Cohn, Harold, 1942-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - D-G, 1950-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 34)
      Correspondents include: Lindsey Decker, Juliette de Lavage, Hugo de Soto, Mojmir Frinta, Eve Garrison, Sid Gotcliffee, and Agnes Gough.
    - H-K, 1946-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 35)
      Correspondents include: Robert Herzberg, Theo Hios, Edward Hopper, Zubel Kachadoorian, Kelly, and Yasuo Kuniyoshi.
    - Jungwirth, Mrs. Leonard, 1950-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Krentzin, Earl, 1961-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - L-O, 1942-1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 38)
      Correspondents include: Elemer A. Lakatos, Matthew Lasinski, Carlos Lopez, Reginald Marsh, Gerald Mast, Walter Midener, Sam Nitro, and Georgia O'Keeffe.
    - Lee-Smith, Hughie, 1953-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Moser, Liselotte, 1930; 1944; 1962-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - P-S, 1944-1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 41)
      Correspondents include: Hobson Pittman, Ogden Pleissner, Arthur Price, Renee Radell, Ruth Reeves, Rossi Reynolds, Ben Rowland, Carl Ruggles, Alfred russell, Walter Sanford, Karl Schmidt-Rottluff, Henry Schnakenberg, Charles Sheeler, Doris Ann Smith, Walt Speck and S.E. Streeter.
    - Simper, Frederick Jr., 1942-1944; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - T-W, 1945-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 43)
      Correspondents include: Donald S. Thrall, George Van Saake, John A. Wedda, Richard Wilt, and Eva Worcester.
    - Watkins, Franklin C., 1964-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 44-45)
    - Watkins, Franklin C., 1964-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Wyeth, Andrew, 1963-1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - With Foreign Scholars, 1945-1964; 3.3; Archival Resource Key; 0.4 Linear feet Box 6
    Includes correspondence with foreign acquaintances and experts on art and art history including Ludwig Baldass, Paul Coremans, Leo van Puyveld, Martin Davies, Therese Bertin-Mourot, Fritz Heinemann, Luigi Coletti, A.B. deVries, and John Steegman.
    Arranged alphabetically by correspondent's country of residence.
    - Austria, 1947-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Correspondents include: Dr. Eckhart Knab, Fritz Novotny, Otto Benesch, and Dr. Karl M. Swoboda
    - Austria, Baldass, Dr. Ludwig, 1948-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Belgium, 1947-1963; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 5)
      Correspondents include: F.J. deWaele, Jean Squilbeck, Jacqueline Folie, A. Janssens de Bisthoven, Paul Coremans, F. Baudouin, Paul Fierens, Dr. J.L. Broeckx, Korneel Goossens, J. Gilissen, and G. Theunis.
    - Belgium, d'Hulst, R.A., 1952-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Belgium, van Puyvelde, Leo, 1947-1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Denmark, Olsen, Harald, 1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - England, 1949-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 9)
      Correspondents include: R.B. Beckett, Peter Bird, L. Burchard, Trenchard Cox, Sir Kenneth McKenzie Clark, C. C. Cunningham, R.H. Dolley, Dennis L.A. Farr, Ralph Fastnedge, Dr. F.M. Godfrey, Geoffrey Grigson, Francis W. Hawcroft, H.D.M. Grier, G. Bernard Hughes, Edward Hutton, Denys Sutton, H.B. Trevor-Cox, E.I. Musgrave, W.G. Constable, R.H. Wilenski, R. Wittkower, Mary Woodall, and Harold Wright.
    - England, Davies, Martin, 1948-1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - England, Edwards, Ralph, 1948-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - England, Garlick, Kenneth, 1949-1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - England, Pope-Hennessy, John, 1952-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - England, Watson, Francis, 1953-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - France, 1946-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 15)
      Correspondents include: I. Pougheol, Madelaine Hours, Renan de LaGodelinais, Marcel Aubert, J.K. van der Haagen, Jacque Dupont, Edouard Michel, Francois Boucher, M.A. Boinet, and Mlle. Chabrier.
    - France, Bertin-Mourot, Therese, 1945-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Germany, 1949-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 17)
      Correspondents include: Dr. Konrad Kaiser, Dr. Ernst Zinner, Walter Kuhn, Ilse R. Manke, Dr. O. Bock von Wulfingen, Charles Ruegg, Dr. Theodor Muller, Katherine von Kallevitz, Dr. A. Hoff, and Dr. Wolfgang Lots.
    - Germany, Heinemann, Dr. Fritz D., 1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Germany, Maedebach, Dr., 1949-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Germany, Vollmer, Dr. Hans, 1947-1950; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Italy, 1946-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 21)
      Correspondents include: Dr. Umbro Apollonio, Edoardo Arslan, Dr. Wart Arslan, Dr. Giacomo Bargellesi, Dr. Ugo Baroncelli, Dino Del Bo, Ferdinando Bologna, Stefano Bottari, Giuliano Briganti, Dr. Fiammetta Gamba, Dr. Nolfo di Carpegna, Dr. Angela Ottino Della Chiesa, Dr. Oreste Ferrari, Lelia Fraccaro, Luciano Gallina, Benno Geiger, Carla Guglielmi, Dr. W. Kronig, Dr. Caterina Marcenaro, Giovanni Mariacher, Paola Michelini, Lino Moretti, Dr. Onello Onelli, Terisio Pignatti, Sergio Ortolani, Annamaria Paris, Dr. Carlo Ludovico Ragghianti, Emilio Tolaini, Giuseppe Tucci, Lionello Venturi, Dr. Carlo Volpe, and Pietro Zampetti
    - Italy, Berenson, Bernard, 1946-1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Italy, Coletti, Luigi, 1947-1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Italy, Morassi, Dr. Antonio, 1949-1953; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Italy, Pallucchini, Rodolfo, 1947-1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Japan, 1951-1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 26)
      Correspondents include: Yoshinobu Masuda and Jiro Arimitsu
    - Miscellaneous Countries, 1953-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 27)
      Correspondents and subjects include: Dr. and Mrs. Bertel Hintze (Finland), Colin McCahon (New Zealand), H. Goetz (India), Necati Dolunay (Turkey), Robert Campbell (Australia), Abbas Katoozian (Iran), and Mohamad Saidi (Iran).
    - Netherlands, 1947-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 28)
      Correspondents include: F. Lugt, Gustav Herkner, Jan H.M. van der Marck, M.A.H. van Es, Dr. S.J. Gudlaugsson, N. Deurvorst, L.J. Bol, G.B. Herkner, Ida Swellengrebel, Dr. J.G. Van Gelder, James J. Post, N. Beets, J. van der Werff, Dr. A. Staring, and K.G. Boon.
    - Netherlands, Gerson, Dr. H., 1950-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - Netherlands, de Vries, Dr. A.B., 1955-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Norway, 1948, 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 31)
      Correspondents and subjects include: Dr. Sigurd Willoch.
    - Scotland, 1949-1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 32)
      Correspondents include: David Baxandall, and E.K. Waterhouse.
    - Sottish National Portrait Gallery, 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 33)
      Correspondents include: R.E. Hutchison and Charles Coleman Sellers.
    - Spain and Portugal, 1949-1955; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 34)
      Correspondents include: Dr. Diego Angulo Iniquez, Pablo d'Almeida, Louis Reis-Santos, Dr. F.J. Sanchez Canton, and Fernando Alvarez de Sotomayor.
    - Switzerland, 1950-1956; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 35)
      Correspondents include: Dr. Paul Ganz and Dr. G.H.A. Clowes
    - Wales, Steegman, John, 1950-1951; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Personal, 1930-1986; 3.4; Archival Resource Key; 0.4 Linear feet Box 6
    IPersonal correspondence is with family and friends, and between E.P. and Constance (note that Mrs. Richardson has annotated some envelopes with information about the contents). There are also condolence letters sent to Constance upon E.P.'s death. Correspondents include Siegfried Aram, Charles Culver, and Carl Ruggles.
    Arranged chronologically, then alphabetically by last name.
    - 1930s-1940s, 1930-1949; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 37)
    - 1950s, 1950-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - 1960s, 1960-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 39)
    - 1970s, 1970-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 40)
    - Aram, Siegfried, 1950-1959; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 41)
    - Condolence Letters to Constance Richardson, 1985-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 42)
    - Constance to E.P. Richardson, 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 43)
    - Culver, Charles, 1940-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 44-47)
    - E.P. to Constance Richardson, 1937-1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 48-49)
    - Family, 1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - Ruggles, Carl, 1941-1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 51)
- Writings and Notes, 1814-1865, 1931-1983; bulk 1931-1983; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 8.3 Linear feet Boxes 7-15
  E.P. Richardson's prominence as an art historian, writer, and expert on collecting is well documented through his prolific writings. Materials include drafts, notes, typescripts, and outlines for articles, exhibition catalog essays, and lectures. Many of the files contain research materials and clippings, correspondence, and other materials related to the event or topic. Also found are research files and publishing documentation for Richardson's books, including Washington Allston: A Study of the Romantic Artist in America (1948), Painting in America (1956), Charles Willson Peale and his World (1983), and American Romantic Painting (1944). Also included are miscellaneous notes and four diaries.
  Series is arranged as 8 subseries.
  4.1: Articles and Essays, 1932-1982
  4.2: Lectures and Talks, 1934-1982
  4.3: Charles Willson Peale files, 1951-1983
  4.4: Painting in America files, 1946-1982
  4.5: Washington Allston files, 1814-1865, 1940-1981
  4.6: Books, 1943-1982
  4.7: Notes, 1931-1982
  4.8: Diaries, 1938-1980
  - Articles and Essays, 1932-1982; 4.1; Archival Resource Key; 1 Linear foot Box 7
    Drafts and typescripts of various writing projects for periodicals as well as exhibition catalogs. Materials include correspondence with galleries and publishers, research materials and clippings, as well as press releases, brochures, and notes.
    Arranged alphabetically by title or subject.
    - "The Adoration with Two Angels," The Detroit Institute of Arts, 1957; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - "Archives of American Art Records of Art Collectors and Dealers: I. Miner K. Kellogg," Art Quarterly, Reprint, 1960; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Articles, Various Typescripts and Drafts, 1932-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 3-5)
    - Baltimore Museum of Art, Comments on Copley and Stuart, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Benjamin Franklin's Chessmen, circa 1930-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - The Cassin Medal, Winterthur Portfolio, 1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Catalog Essays, Typescripts and Drafts, 1962-1964; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Copley's New York Portraits, Winterthur Portfolio II, 1964-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - The Curse of Modern Art, circa 1930-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - The Dance, A Study on Paintings of Dancing Children, 1963-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Day, Sherman, 1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Dickson, Age of Dunlap, Review, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Eichholtz, Jacob, 1939-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 15-16)
    - Fleischman Collection, 1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Flemish Painting Catalog, Collecting Flemish Art in America, 1959-1960, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Flemish Painting Catalog, Corpus, 1955-1962; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Grigaut, Paul, Art Quarterly, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Hals, Frans, An Important Showing of Hals, circa 1930-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Howald, The Ferdinand Howald Collection, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - "Painting in Philadelphia, 1750-1770", 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - "Painting on the Eve of the Revolution", 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Reviews of Books and MSS, 1960-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Suhr, William, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - "Three Hundred Years of American Painting,"USIA Exhibition Catalog, 1957-1958; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 27-28)
    - Trumbull's Portrait of Washington, Winterthur Portfolio III, 1965-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - Watkins, Franklin, A Painter's Search for Meaning, The Atlantic Monthly, 1965-1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - Wyeth, Andrew, 1964-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Lectures and Talks, 1934-1982; 4.2; Archival Resource Key; 1.7 Linear feet Boxes 8-9
    Documents the frequent lectures and gallery talks given by Richardson to museums, galleries, community centers, historical societies and committees, and universities. Many files also include administrative correspondence regarding compensation, schedules, and travel, as well as handwritten notes and outlines of individual lectures. A number of lectures were for the Detroit Art Market and Youth Art Month during the period Richardson was Education Secretary at the Detroit Institute of Arts.
    Arranged alphabetically by lecture location.
    - Allentown Art Museum, Members' Lecture Series, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - American Philosophical Society, The Muses and the Museum, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 2)